Dick Wingert Cartoons
Dick Wingert Cartoons
1956-1966.
Wingert, Dick, 1919-
5.4 linear ft.
1,931 original daily cartoons and 146 original Sunday cartoons from the comic strip Hubert.
149482
Biographical History
Richard C. Wingert (1919-1993), commonly known as Dick Wingert, was an American cartoonist and creator of the comic strip Hubert.
Born in Cedar Rapids, Iowa on January 15, 1919, Wingert's father was a printer who was skeptical of artists and hoped his son would go into business with him. But a high school art teacher helped Wingert secure a three year scholarship to the John Herren Art Institute in Indianapolis starting in 1937. While a student, Wingert assumed he would work in illustration.
It was Wingert's service in WWII that led to his career as a nationally syndicated cartoonist. Wingert graduated in 1940 and was inducted into the Army in February 1941. After spending a year in Louisiana with the 34th Infantry Division he was sent to Ireland in 1942. Wingert submitted samples to the newly re-established Stars and Stripes. After several of his cartoons were printed, Wingert requested a transfer to the Stars and Stripes division and was moved to London. Here he spent the rest of the war and created his main character "Hubert"—an unshaven, baffled and disheveled GI popular with deployed readers. Hubert started as an illustration and later became a regular single panel cartoon.
Wingert talked to fellow soldiers and this shared, collective experience of being in the military provided Wingert with ideas. In the foreword to a Hubert compilation published in 1955, Wingert explained, “The army is a wonderful place for a cartoonist to start. There is no end of material and all you have to do is make a humorous comment on how you personally feel about any given situation of army life and you have a million other guys who feel the same way you do."
Following the end of the war, Wingert returned to the United States eventually settling in Westport, Connecticut. William Randolph Hearst Jr., whom Wingert had met during the war, suggested he submit cartoons to the New York syndicates. King Features Syndicate picked up Hubert as a daily strip which debuted December 3, 1945. Wingert later suggested Hearst provided assistance (unbeknownst to him at the time) in securing this contract with King Features.
Wingert transitioned Hubert to civilian life and a Sunday strip was added February 3, 1946. Wingert briefly revisited his time in Europe with the military when he and other cartoonists including Gus Edson, Al Posen and Bob Montana participated in a USO cartoonists tour in October 1952. Though Wingert reportedly employed a few assistants over the years—Tex Blaisdell and Frank Johnson are commonly named—he remained the primary artistic presence on the strip through to the end of its run. Dick Wingert died November 24, 1993 in Indiana of an aneurysm.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Dick Wingert Cartoons collection contains 1,931 original daily cartoons and 146 original Sunday cartoons from the comic strip Hubert (1956-1966). The strip features main character Hubert Dooley, whose lack of sophistication and bad luck provide the punch line. Hubert bumbles through life at the office and Hubert's barbs with his mother-in-law at home serve as a running gag.
Daily strips are a single panel and Sunday strips contain three rows and multiple panels.
Most captions are written in pencil at the bottom or on the reverse. The remainder are printed and pasted on. Caption revisions are present on some cartoons. "Engraved by CP" is stamped on the back of many cartoons. The Sunday strips were created as three separate pieces taped together. Materials include ink, traces of pencil, varying weights of illustration board and zipatone.
Arrangement of the Collection
Daily and Sunday cartoons are arranged separately in chronological order.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
Two copies of the first edition of a compilation titled Hubert (Arbogast: Otterbach-Kaiserslautern, Germany c1955) have been removed from the collection and sent to Rare Books for cataloging
Subject and Genre Headings
Wingert, Dick, 1919-; King Features Syndicate.; Hubert (comic strip); Art -- Cartoonists; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Comic books, strips, etc. -- United States.; Cartoons (humorous images); Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dick Wingert, 1967.
Inventory
- Hubert, Click here for a detailed inventory.
  - Daily cartoons, 1931 Cartoons range from 6" x 6" to 8 1/2" x 9".
    - 1956 (Box 1)
    - 1957 (Box 2)
    - 1958 (Box 3)
    - 1961 Feb - 1962 May (Box 4)
    - 1962 Jun - 1963 May (Box 5)
    - 1963 Jun - 1964 Mar (Box 6)
    - 1964 Apr - 1965 Feb (Box 7)
    - 1965 Mar - 1966 Jan (Box 8)
  - Sunday cartoons, 146 15" x 22 1/4"
    - 1959 - 1960, Contains one undated Sunday cartoon (Oversize 1)
    - 1961 - 1962 (Oversize 2)